okay
minut watch it
bre
e e
come to the Golden
Moon
e
e e
look out the window the
sky blue
sky e
watch any tension in your
face corners of your
mouth
forehead and especially the tops of your
eyelids the upper part of your Island
watch the mountains watch the valley
come back to the golden
room sit with your
teacher their hands are on your hand
their hands are touching your hand
try to feel a sense of love sense of
contentment for being
there that you don't need to go anywhere
else you have nothing else to
do just be happy being there with their
hands on your head
relax breathe
slow just their hands on your the only
meditation
object
e
e e
slowly bring your mind back to this
room then you can open your eyes
so we're almost to the top of the
chart
uh we have gotten uh s cha which means
uh single pointed
mind the elephant is all white now
there's no
dullness there's no
agitation there's good and L
and then at at scene number
28 you see uh level
9 and it's
yamb again yamba means
equals
s and then uh d means Sy probably the
word think came from
T so some
traditionally
Samad or you could
say uh sitting in
equilibrium you could call the semi
equilibrium is a state
between it's it's a natural state
between the two extremes of the driving
wheel the steering wheel okay you are
spreading a very effortless path uh down
the middle of the two extremes of
dullness and agitation
okay
and then he says this
is and we'll talk about that
I like that thing the Joker
does
uh and it's achieved by uh you by the
way the elephant is lying down okay the
elephant has been controlled completely
who who's the elephant by himself the
elephant is your own mind okay so he's
like the mind is his servant now okay
and we our minds tend to control us and
at at level number nine samama you are
controlling the mind okay the mind's at
your beck and
call and I think uh as you meditated you
got the feeling of what it was like how
fast the Mind moves I don't know if
you've come across that yet but uh it's
it's Instant by instant it moves like
lightning you know and you're trying
to You See It Go off the object and you
bring it back on the object and it all
takes place in an instant you know and
then 30 seconds later it's off again and
so you think you have to get used to
moving fast inside your
mind I I don't know if an elephant is so
good I think more like a a bird or
something it moves very fast or if
you've ever tried to catch a lizard with
your hands and they just they move and
they even look like this you know and
and the mind is like that okay m
what I thought I would do is you know
this is level 9 and there's still some
things going on up
here okay after level 9 so I thought we
could go there today and start working
on what happens after level 9 okay so
here we go
uh it's it's significant that the text
calls it D DM means as we said yesterday
a state of mind which is still in the
desire realm
so Buddhism talks about and also
Hinduism but they talk about three
Realms right three three Loca there
three Realms and
um in a in a very minor sense it refers
to above the Earth meaning Birds on the
earth meaning animals and below the
Earth or below the sea meaning fish or
groundhogs uh that's not what they mean
here okay that's not Tri Loa
here Trea here there's
a causal treca and there's a resulting
treca there's three
Realms of cause and there's three Realms
of result so you have to get used to
that
idea the three classical Realms are uh D
Suk Su d means desire
real uh Suk means form realm
rup and then Su means formless realm
okay when you speak of these
three as results okay when you speak of
these three Realms as
results uh the the desire realm is is
this world that we're in now and most of
us have never seen the other two Realms
okay they exist uh what do you call
them supposedly the form realm is
is higher than this realm
physically uh a lot of people would say
it's just a parallel universe it's going
on Parallel to this
realm and then uh the formless realm has
no gross form no gross physical
matter uh
and what they're characterized like this
dcom as I said yesterday the first
dilemma describes it as uh desire for
food and sex mainly so this is a realm
where uh are many people's primary
motivation is food sex I guess you
should add television now uh so uh I see
these incredible numbers like that
people spend an average of six hours on
T TV or or children spend an average of8
hours texting and I I can't believe it I
can't imagine I that because they say
throw us in that means the other people
are doing like 16 hours or something I
don't
know uh but it's mainly uh a realm where
we are focused on desire for uh lower
Pleasures all right and that's what
that's what characterizes our realm uh
there's a higher realm called the form
real uh and that's
like when you read in Greek mythology of
a Greek Paradise or something and
there's what do you call job or no I
don't know these Greek gods you know you
saw the movie right uh and they're all
like very
powerful uh
bickering uh beings and and uh they have
special powers and and uh they live very
long
lives and that's called a a form real
okay they're why is it called form real
because their bodies are extraordinary
they they their forms are very beautiful
and that realm is
distinguished by the beauty of their
forms and their world which we would
almost consider a paradise
okay
uh or in in Indra or or you know people
I don't know
Brahma like that this is where these
people stay
um and then the formless
realm uh is uh these mainly the people
there they exist their bodies are a very
very subtle form of Prana or something
they don't have any physical visable
bodies uh not gross physical they have
very very subtle physical bodies which
you can't see and then they just exist
as mine they're just mental beings okay
so that realm is said to have no
physical location it's said that if you
died in the desire realm today sitting
in this room your mind would enter the
form formless realm just there so
there's no uh
Bardock there's no uh spirit being
between dying here and going to the
formless realm because the function of a
b b is like a spirit being okay bar bar
means in between par in between your
death and your rebirth so traditionally
they say that uh you become after you
die in this realm you become a spirit
being and then that being has special
abilities to
travel fantastic distances
in at faster than the speed of light
okay so that at the speed of thought
that being can travel distances which
which traditionally is supposed to
explain why well it does explain why you
could be born on another planet okay so
you could die in this realm you you
become a barle a spirit being and then
at the speed of thought you can arrive
on another planet and be born there
okay so there's no B for someone
entering the formless
realm uh because they don't have
anywhere to go you just die here and you
enter the formless realm
here so those are
the and the form and formless Realms are
said to be Realms of
complacency uh you are powerful you are
beautiful uh nothing ever goes wrong
much and uh you could say almost like a
worldly
God and the life lifespans there are
very long
okay and then there's this poignant
description of uh the the the final
weeks of a of a of a person in the form
or formless realm that their karma
begins to wear out and then uh they have
a premonition of their death they they
have a they see their coming death
and then their body for the first time
produces uh sweat perspiration they
start to smell like they've never even
had to Bath because they had these
golden perfect bodies and then the body
starts to deteriorate and it starts to
smell bur and then
uh and they start to lose
their call like Radiance and then the
other beings there are uh what do you
call repulsed
by their appearance and and then there's
this sad uh description of what it's
like to be a being who has lived in a
paradise for 10,000 years and then the
last few weeks uh your
friends all these other pleasure beings
they're just having a good time you know
and then you are suddenly you are
suddenly not very attractive and they
just don't want to be around you and
everyone what do you call it they shun
you and then uh then they say that the
suffering of those few weeks is equal to
the pleasure of the 10,000 years to be
to after 10,000 years to be to be
rejected by the other pleasure seekers
in your realm and then they
die uh and then they say that uh they
say that because you have used up your
debit card in the 10,000 years of
pleasure that those beings almost in
very ibly uh go to a lower realm
okay and we learned with Nick yesterday
that go to a lower realm is a misnomer
right we learned yesterday that you
don't go to a lower
realm your your your perception shift
slightly your mental seeds shift
slightly you
know in other words you don't for a
person who understands
emptiness they can appreciate the
teaching on
rebirth because they understand that
it's not really the case that you die
and go somewhere it's just that the
seeds in your mind shift
slightly you know and to say that that's
not possible or that's weird
or then that's that's as weird as to say
there's no death you see because the
shift from living to dead the shift from
having Consciousness to not having
Consciousness that's about as radical a
shift as the mind can do
to be to go from mind to no mind is the
most radical sh we're not talking you
see things differently we're
talking the very seeds for
Consciousness stop wear out and then
you're not conscious okay you die so to
to say that the mind could go from
awareness to non-awareness
uh then everything between can happen
Okay you can can go from uh pleasantly
warm to too
hot uh you can go from healthy to a
sniveling mess uh you can go from you
know everyone smiling at you to suddenly
everyone hates you you know uh these are
just shifts of the seeds and they happen
to
everybody uh so it's not a big deal that
your seeds could
shift after some trauma you know after
being hit by car or or something and
then and then your seats would shift and
you would see things completely
different okay so it's not it's not a
stretch for a person who understands
emptiness to be
concerned strongly about the
extraordinary shifts that the mind can
make in a negative sense you see you
could go to a hell realm in 10 seconds
uh it's not impossible if you understand
emptiness it's not at all impossible cuz
you're not going to a hell room uh your
your your seeds are shifting and they've
been shifting your whole life and it's
just a bigger shift in a positive
sense uh you can use that phenomenon to
become a a Buddha okay an enlightened
being you can also shift the other way
you could have a radical shift out of
this reality into a a reality where you
are you are the Buddha of a Planet you
know you are the savior of a planet you
could you could also have that shift
that's the shift we're trying to trigger
with our meditation
okay so those are the three Realms
desire realm form realm formulus realm
now there are certain seeds which get
you into those three Realms okay there
are certain mental seeds you have to
plant to get into those three
Realms then we talk about the causal
three Realms okay
the causal three rooms so don't be
confused in scripture it's confusing it
took me a long
time gashi there was a gashi gelon which
is a Corruption of
gon a Mongol he taught me this it was
very
beautiful
uh so don't be confused between the
three Realms as as caal and the three
Realms as resultant we just described
the three Realms as resultant
to get into those three Realms you have
to be in a certain State of Mind for
much of your current life to go to one
of those three Realms after you
die right or so what shall we say to
project those three Realms after you die
uh there are certain causes or states of
mind you have to be in habitually in
this life okay what are
they uh for the desire realm you just
have to be who you are you know just a
normal distracted mind uh will throw you
into the desire realm all right uh don't
forget desire realm doesn't just mean
humans it also means hell beings uh
insects uh like that okay so desire
Realm by the way they say desire realm
is the best place to be born for a a
spiritual practitioner because of the
desirable mix of pain and pleasure okay
so you have enough
pleasure not to be in pain all the time
not to be mindless with
pain and then you you have enough pain
that it it's not like the form realm
where you're just hanging out in a
paradise until until you start to smell
okay uh they say the desire realm is is
is
desirable for our spiritual practice
okay so anyway just to keep a normal
state of mind would get you into the
desire room after you
die and again get in is a is a deceptive
word to use right we should
say living in a having a state of mind
that we have now you know mostly focused
on food or or success or fame or money
or sex these these these states of
mind will cause you to see a desire
realm in the way you see a pen or a Choy
right it's the same they will cause you
to see your world as a desire room
uh then the form
room if you wanted to get to a form room
if you wanted to be Indra
or Shiva or or Brahma or something like
that
um you can get there by spending much of
your current life in deep states of
meditation okay in very very deep states
of
meditation and that's called sang okay s
than
uhana Samaya okay something DBA means
DBA means
vow but it also means uh self-control
like Yama okay Yama and Yama so DBA
means vow or
self-control something means deep
meditation
Diana so
Diana uh
Diana
svara or Diana
Samaya uh these would mean it's very
funny if you spend a lot of time
meditating in this realm you
can project a for after you die
because during the AC of meditation you
can't do all the naughty things you
usually do
okay okay you can't lie to somebody body
when you're in a deep state of
meditation uh you can't wish that
someone would fall off a truck uh your
exboyfriend
um uh while your mind is in deep
meditation you see you can't uh you
can't steal something when your mind is
in deep meditation so it's you could
call it
default right uh default goodness all
right like you just don't have time to
do all your
normal small bad Deeds your normal flow
of small constant bad Deeds which are
mostly mental you know
like I really wish that the lady
who I I hope she slips on the eyes or
something like that you know like just
little things that fly through your mind
you know of course we wouldn't want her
to sip on the ice but the thought does
fly through your mind sometimes okay
then when you're in a state of deep
meditation you can't have those thoughts
and and so by default you you don't
collect the Bad Karma that you normally
would and then you can go to a form
realm okay you can project a form realm
after you die an in formless realm would
require even deeper
concentration okay so the the three
Realms as causes are normal State of
Mind pretty deep meditation and
extremely deep meditation that three
Realms as a results are the the world
you know a parad a temporary parad
Physical Realm and then a a realm where
the beings only have Minds okay only
live in their minds as Minds why are we
talking about
this level
9 okay level
nine is still a state of mind that would
throw which would project the desire
realm after you done it still do him
it's still a state of mind
which is not even deep enough yet to
throw you into a paradise after you die
okay which implies that there
are there are about uh eight levels of
meditation higher there are eight higher
levels of meditation okay
um but we get off
here and and use the meditation to go
see emptiness okay we get off here all
right we we don't well just about here
we get off at 9 plus okay but we don't
go up to 17 all right uh so there are
deeper meditations you can do deeper in
the sense that you would be even more
uncheckable they could put French
McDonald french fries and a Big
Mac uh not just the french fries but
with the Big Mac and an Apple Fritter
pie under your your nose and you would
be oblivious okay you wouldn't smell
anything your concentration be so good
and then they could play Jimmy Hendrick
you know uh in your eye uh iPod thing at
full volume in in with the Apple
earphones which are really good right uh
and you wouldn't hear anything okay they
could tune it up all the way and put it
in your ears and you wouldn't hear
anything that's how deep the there are
places you can
go um but they're not what we want
okay that's just a bigger telescope on
the gun okay that like that's a
telescope that goes 5 miles or 10 miles
but the deer we want to shoot is is
right around it's not it's about 200
yards away we don't need a a a a
telescope on our rifle that goes 20 mil
okay cuz what the deer we're after is is
right around us it's like a 100 yards
away and that's emptiness okay now all
we want to do is get the mind calm
enough to see emptiness seeing emptiness
they always compared I like that
metaphor uh is like a moon reflecting on
the water okay and if the lake water is
Ripple Rippling then then the Moon is
Rippling and you can't see it very
clearly okay the the idea is get the
Mind still enough like still water and
then emptiness which is the moon can
reflect in the water and then you can
see it clearly Okay so so we just have
to get up to a certain amount
of you could still see the moon if
there's a a Cricut fell in the water and
he's like doing this and this tiny
little Ripple you know like it doesn't
have to
be completely motionless you see it's
enough you don't have to go higher in
concentration all right so this is still
a this is still a state of mind in the
desire realm but when I say in the
desire realm you know I mean
not not yeah just as a cause okay in the
desire realm doesn't mean you're sitting
in the desire desire realm with that
State of Mind in your head it doesn't
mean that when I say in the desire realm
referring to a state of meditation you
should you should automatically think oh
he means a meditation which is deep
enough or not so deep that it would keep
me in the desire around me if I died it
would keep projecting desire realm if I
die so when I say your mind is still in
the desire realm I don't mean that
you're sitting in this realm with a
brain that's thinking like that I mean
if you died at that moment your mind
would project a desire room okay so you
have to be careful when they call it
desire realm state of meditation they
don't mean you're sitting in the desire
realm they mean if you died at that
moment that mind would project another
desire okay so I have a question for you
which you can nod or shake your head uh
would it be possible to enter a form
real meditation with your body sitting
in the desire
room yeah so could we Loosely say you
would be sitting in the desire room and
you would be in the form realm you could
say that okay meaning your state of mind
was such that if you died at that moment
you would project a form real okay like
that and to be more accurate I'd have to
say
it's not just the state of mind you have
at the moment of death okay it's like
where did you spend most of your time
you know so people born in the form
realm are by definition people who spend
over half their time in their life in in
deep
meditation they spend over half the
hours of their life in deep meditation
okay so you can guess how many people on
this planet are going to a
formal okay it's like I don't know zero
or T I don't know that we always think
there must be somebody
somewhere and they think we're here
doing it
also okay we think there's somebody in
India probably up near
rishikes who's who's meditating enough
to get to the formal and they think
somebody over in America is trying is
some Buddhist group must be doing it so
let's try you let's
meditation watch your
breath please e
what what I find easiest watching the
breath is to pick a tiny point in the
tip of my
nostrils and just observe the feeling
the sort of the cool feeling of breath
touching that little patch of
skin then that becomes my single point I
find it distracting to try to watch the
whole breath
uh in and out I just try to focus on a
tiny patch of
skin uh at the tip of the
nostril which is alternately cooled and
heated by the passage of
breath in general in meditation the
smaller you can make the physical object
or the mental object the better the
concentration so you could start out
with a/2 inch p P of the inside of your
nostril and you could go to a quar inch
and then go to
a a like a a pin a needle tip patch of
skin and then that will help your
concentration
e e
come to the Golden
Moon deep
liquid
orangish warm
shining gold color flowing in through
the
windows and making all the objects in
the room like giving them a golden
cust
e e
stay with that golden
color stay with that golden
light again try to call up a feeling
ofar even now before your Lama comes try
to
feel that you are totally contented in
the room the room
is so
beautiful and the anticipation of your
teacher coming
is so sweet and you don't really have
any other hope in the world but to stay
in that golden room
so enjoy deeply and be deeply contented
with the
gold the the room of golden
light e
look at the blue of the
sky try to bring up
bypass dullness and agitation by going
straight to
nor enjoy this guy feel contented with
this guy the beauty of this guy
then bring your mind down to the
mountains and the valley
and then bring your mind back to the
golden room
ask your teacher to come to the room
and look on your teacher look on your
teacher
face and the face is covered in the same
Golden Light
stay there with their
face try to feel
contentment
e
e e
and come back to this one
slowly open your
eyes so next time we'll cover
the I don't know then he gets to ride on
the
elephant
okay and then he doesn't need to ride he
can
fly all right so that's coming right
[Music]
sh
of show